now let's talk about the return address
stack predictor or Ras we have seen that
there are several types of branches that
we need to predict for conditional
branches we need to predict the
direction is it taken or not and by now
we have seen a number of predictors that
predict Direction reasonably well for
these types of things if this branch is
taken we will need to also predict the
target address and for that a simple btb
that just remembers the previous Target
when the branch was taken will do just
fine because we always have the same
Target another type of branches are
unconditional jumps function calls Etc
as far as their direction is concerned
it's trivial they are always
taken so even the simplest predictor of
the direction predictor type will do
well on these as far as the target
prediction is concerned most of these
either jump to a label or call a
specific function so a simple btb that
just remembers the previous Target when
this instruction was executed will do
just fine so it looks like we have
handled both the direction and the
target for most of the common Branch
types however there is a type of Branch
specifically the function returns which
is always taken so the direction
prediction will do just fine but the
target is often difficult to predict if
this function is always called from the
same place then the return will always
jump back to the same location and in
that case the the btb will do fine but
usually we create a function so that it
can be called from multiple places in
the program something like this we have
an instruction that can call this
function somewhere else in the program
we have another instruction that can
call the same function this function has
a return instruction and now the problem
is that this return instruction should
either jump here or here depending on
where it was called from the btb in this
case will not do too well why well
because when we call this and return
here the btb will remember that this is
the target address then we reach this
point call again return we should be
returning here but the btb is predicting
this so we have a misprediction the btb
now will learn that this is the correct
Target next we come back to this code
again and again the btb is predicting
here while we should be returning here
and then again and again so it never
predicts correctly so the question is
how can we predict returns accurately